Okay
good morning.
We are
on today's דף מ"ט. Daf Mem Tes. We're going to pick up
on מ"ח עמוד ב'. Mem Ches Amud Beis. The issue we're dealing
with right now is people executed by the king. Who inherits their
property? Do their heirs inherit or does the king get it? And
we're in the middle actually we're picking up with
יואב. Yoav.
That's where we are.
בשלמא Bishlama two lines down in where the lines get wide in
מ"ח עמוד ב'. Mem Ches Amud Beis. I think that's where we
were.
So actually it's interesting because the last time I did the דף
Daf over here for the group this is a continuation of what
yeah it's like the... if you just to go back remember there's
the whole thing with מיכל, Michal, you know the two daughters but
then we also were talking about, you know about אבנר בן נר
Avner ben Ner then just to go back a little bit.
So remember that guy עשהאל? Asael? We were talking about him then.
So עשהאל Asael was very fleet footed and there were a couple
of brothers. So there was יואב Yoav and עשהאל Asael who were
brothers and there's this whole like schism in the king, you know
this is where... that's how we got into it the last time
about איש בושת Ish-bosheth and מפיבושת Mephibosheth and then the wife of...
one of דוד's David wives, you know daughters of שאול Shaul being
given to one and then the other... oh can it be this
guy was really the other guy? Anyway we're not going to go
back to that but we did talk about עשהאל Asael and then
people you know then
אבנר Avner and יואב.
Yoav. So this really is a continuation of that to some way.
So anyway
עשהאל's Asael very fleet footed was running after
אבנר Avner and then אבנר Avner said listen just don't you know
you're not going to beat me right? You know אבנר Avner was
one of the generals. And the reason we got into that was
because אבנר Avner was backing... was backing מפיבושת... Mephibosheth... was backing איש
בושת. Ish-bosheth. He made him I think... he made him like you
know a king and lots of names so I'm trying to get
it all straight. But anyway so that's what he did and then
you know עשהאל Asael was running... anyway so עשהאל Asael was running
after him. אבנר Avner said you know desist and then אבנר Avner
you know got him anyway in the fifth rib. That was and
he killed him. יואב Yoav was his brother so יואב Yoav obviously
would not have been happy about this and
the...
where was it? They quote the פסוקים pesukim over
here... שמואל ב' Shmuel Beis I think. שמואל ב' Shmuel Beis let's
look. It's in the beginning of שמואל ב'. Shmuel Beis. Let me
try to find it.
I'm sorry are you on
וינס יואב? Vayanas Yoav? Well I'm going to do that beforehand because
the גמרא Gemara is going to
reference it was אבנר Avner it was איש בושת Ish-bosheth right.
So...
yeah so then that's what it was. אבנר Avner and יואב Yoav
says okay like the guys are going to
fight then עשהאל Asael is running after him. אבנר Avner kills him
and then that's and that's how we got into it. דוד David
made a big show of mourning to say that he didn't want
to kill אבנר Avner that's... we got into it now coming back
to you. So you know then everyone believes him right? Because we
said at the beginning the people wanted to kill דוד David and
they realized how sincere he was and he won them over. So
this is a continuation of the story.
So he יואב Yoav later on ended up
not backing דוד David is a little bit later.
There unfortunately you know there were lots of rebellions within דוד's David
own family like אדוניה בן חגית Adoniyah ben Chaggit saying אני אמלוך.
Ani Emlach. Then you have also the very...
the very famous story about his other son, you know בני אבשלום,
Beni Avshalom, אבשלום בני Avshalom Beni who also rebelled against דוד David
and you know was killed. So יואב Yoav had killed
him
and
within that
and we're going to be quoting these
פסוקים... pesukim... let's pick up from here.
והשמועה באה עד יואב
Ve-shamuah ba'ah ad Yoav so יואב Yoav then... כי יואב נטה אחרי
אדוניה. Ki Yoav natah acharei Adoniyah. I'm reading the פסוקים pesukim in
נביא Navi
because we're going to make
reference to all of these.
I'm just going
to read it once.
So we're over here? Which two lines from where it gets wide
in מ"ח עמוד
ב'?
Mem Ches
Amud Beis?
Which is וינס יואב? Vayanas Yoav? Yeah and the full quote is
what we're going to start from.
Well I'm going to give you a little bit of the story
behind it because we're going to be reading all this anyway so
might as well just read it once. כי
יואב נטה אחרי אדוניה. Ki Yoav natah acharei Adoniyah. So יואב Yoav
turned... in other words followed back... went with. whatever you want to
say that means, like you know, not just and considering he was
the military, you know, that that's a statement. You know what I
mean?
Now נטה אחרי אדוניה, nata acharei Adoniya, אדוניה's Adoniya one of the
sons of דוד David who was also rebelling. ואחרי אבשלום לא נטה.
Ve'acharei Avshalom lo nata. But he didn't he didn't back אבשלום. Avshalom.
וינס יואב אל אהל ה' ויחזק בקרנות
המזבח. Vayanos Yoav el Ohel Hashem vayachazek bekarnot hamizbe'ach. So this is
where people get the common like you know thing of sanctuary in
a church, right? So he went to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, he's holding
on literally to the horns of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you know, because
they have these like four horns of the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. So already enough this is enough of a of a
offense to be killed, right? He's מורד במלכות mored bemalchut literally, right?
So ויגד למלך שלמה כי נס יואב. Vayugad lamelech Shlomo ki nas
Yoav. Now דוד's David dead by now. So שלמה Shlomo is is
the king. יואב Yoav ran away to there. והנה אצל המזבח. Vehineh
etzel hamizbe'ach. וישלח שלמה את בניהו בן יהוידע לאמר לך פגע בו.
Vayishlach Shlomo et Benayahu ben Yehoyada lemor lech pga bo. So he
sends בניהו Benayahu says, you know, alright, you know, take care of
him meaning like kill him. לך פגע בו. lech pga bo. ויבא
בניהו אל אהל ה'. Vayavo Benayahu el Ohel Hashem. So I'm going
to read this and you know we're going to see what the
גמרא Gemara does, you know, going to ask what you think. ויבא
בניהו אל אהל ה' ויאמר אליו כה אמר המלך צא. Vayavo Benayahu
el Ohel Hashem vayomer eilav koh amar hamelech tze.
The king said he got to get out of here. ויאמר לא
כי פה אמות. Vayomer lo ki po amut. You kidding me? I'm
not. You got to get me here if you're going to if
you're going to you know thinking obviously they're not going to get
him in you know in the where המזבח hamizbe'ach is, right? Like
you know spill cold blood in the משכן Mishkan or the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash or wherever, right? וישב בניהו אל המלך דבר לאמר
כה דבר יואב וכה ענני. Vayashev Benayahu el hamelech davar lemor koh
diber Yoav vechoh anani. So בניהו Benayahu goes back to the king
and says this is what יואב Yoav told me, this is what
I you know this is this is you know this is what
he answered me, you know seems like this whole extended conversation but
the really you know over here all it is is just like
you know three words, right? Four words, לא כי פה אמות. Lo
ki po amut. So ויאמר לו המלך עשה כאשר דבר ופגע בו
וקברתו. Vayomer lo hamelech aseh ka'asher diber ufga bo ukvartu. Okay,
do what he says. Kill him and bury him. So what
do you mean do as he says? You know meaning kill if
I were to say what does it mean do as he says?
What do you all say? He just said four words. לא כי
פה אמות, Lo ki po amut, right? I'm going to die here.
So he says alright kill him there, right?
So that's that's I mean that's פשט, pshat, right? Yeah and המאירי
haMeiri says they're to take it, but we'll see.
So kill him there and then bury him. והסירות דמי חנם אשר
שפך יואב מעלי ומעל בית אבי. Vahasirota dmei chinam asher shafach Yoav
me'alai ume'al beit avi.
And then you'll you know if you will like you'll atone, you'll
you'll literally like remove the you know the guilt of the blood
of the two people he killed which was which were like אבנר
בן נר, Avner ben Ner, right? That was that whole show of
mourning
that דוד David was doing, right? So you know so this needed
to be avenged because meanwhile you know יואב Yoav was was still
around until until this point. והשיב ה' את דמו על ראשו אשר
פגע בשני אנשים צדיקים וטובים ממנו. Veheshiv Hashem et damo al rosho
asher pga bishnei anashim tzadikim vetovim mimenu.
So God will you know basically
bring the guilt of down from the blood that of the people
he killed, two people better than him. ויהרגם בחרב ואבי דוד לא
ידע. Vayahargem bacherev va'avi David lo yada. את אבנר בן נר. Et
Avner ben Ner. He says it. שר צבא ישראל ואת עמשא בן
יתר שר צבא יהודה. Sar tzva Yisrael ve'et Amasa ben Yeter sar
tzva Yehuda.
He killed אבנר Avner and he killed עמשא. Amasa. And אבנר Avner
killed עשהאל. Asahel. Just remember that. You know everyone's killing each other
here. So you know so אבנר Avner killed killed עשהאל Asahel and
יואב Yoav killed אבנר, Avner, right? And that's what he's saying.
It's like the end of Macbeth.
So yeah so then so so now he's saying you know יואב
Yoav needs to be killed. One of the reasons is because he
you know killed these two guys, right? And also remember I said
he's מורד במלכות, mored bemalchut, right? He's backing one you know one
of these other sons of דוד. David. So ושבו דמיהם בראש יואב
ובראש זרעו לעולם. Veshavu dmeihem berosh Yoav uverosh zaro le'olam. This is
and then you know his the blood will be on the ראש
rosh of יואב Yoav and the ראש rosh and the head of
his progeny forever. ולדוד ולזרעו ולביתו ולכסאו יהיה שלום עד עולם מעם
ה'. UleDavid ulezaro uleveito ulechiso yihyeh shalom ad olam me'im Hashem. Then
but for דוד David and for his... Just hidden in text somehow
that it's not live online.
It's not?
Oh that's too bad. Okay let's do that again
but it's not live. Okay it's not
live?
Alright alright let's try now. Is it live now? Tell tell her
to try it.
I just got a message it's live.
Okay fine. Alright so sorry for all of you who missed it
I was going through the history of of what the גמרא's Gemara
דף daf today which is 49. We're picking up the three two
lines down
48 עמוד ב'. amud bet. So the story basically is the short
of it you know is that יואב Yoav who killed two people
well he killed many more people he was a you know after
all military leader but he killed אבנר Avner and he killed עמשא
Amasa and אבנר Avner had killed עשהאל. Asahel. עשהאל Asahel was יואב's
Yoav brother. So now you know יואב Yoav ran to the מזבח
mizbe'ach is claiming sanctuary.
He says no I'm going to die here and שלמה Shlomo was
now king says to בניהו Benayahu you know okay. Fine, kill him
there. This is what it seems like. And he says, okay, by
killing יואב, Yoav,
pardon me, by killing
יואב, Yoav, we'll atone for the blood of the innocent people that
he killed, that יואב Yoav killed, and as for דוד David and
his children, meaning
שלמה, Shlomo, there'll be peace. Then בניהו בן יהוידע Benayahu ben Yehoyada
kills him, ויפגע בו וימיתהו ויקבר בביתו במדבר, Vayifga bo vayimitehu, vayikaber
beveito bamidbar, and
then he was buried in his house in the desert.
Okay, and then בניהו Benayahu took יואב's Yoav position
as a military leader. Fine. So that's what that is and then
we're going to see how the גמרא Gemara deals with all these
פסוקים. pesukim. We needed to do this, you'll see. ובשלמא למאן דאמר
נכסיו למלך, Uvishlama lemandamar nechasav lammelekh, three lines down on עמוד ב
amud bet on the wide lines, היינו דכתיב וינס יואב אל אהל
ה׳ ויחזק בקרנות המזבח. Hainu dikhtiv vayanos Yoav el ohel Hashem vayakhazek
bekarnot hammizbe'ach.
So
if you're going to say that the
king
inherits, if you will, or gets,
expropriates is really the right word, the property of someone who rebelled
against him, then we can understand, I mean, it's a weird way
of looking at this, but that's why we can understand that יואב
Yoav went to the אהל ה׳ ohel Hashem to, literally the temple
of God, basically the משכן, Mishkan, then and
he
grabbed and he held on to the קרנות, karnot, the horns, literally,
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. וכתיב ויאמר לא כי
פה אמות. Vikhtiv vayomer lo ki po amut. There's no other way
to say it. So לא—no, Lo I'm going to die here. So
meaning why? Because I don't want the king to get my property.
That's what they're saying as opposed to, well, I don't want to
die.
אלא למאן דאמר נכסיו ליורשים מאי נפקא ליה מיניה Ella lemandamar nechasav
leyoreshim, mai nafa-ka leh mineh? So why, if the יורשים yoreshim are
going to get it, why is he so insistent on staying there?
So the obvious answer is חיי שעה. Chayyei sha'ah. He wanted to
not die, right? So it's nothing to do with who gets his
property. He could still be either case that יורשים yoreshim get it
or he just wanted to stay alive a little bit longer. Okay,
let's go on. וישב בניהו את המלך דבר לאמר כה דבר יואב
וכה ענני. Vayashev Benayahu et hammelekh davar lemor ko dibber Yoav vekho
anani. So
oh, this is what יואב Yoav said and this is what he
answered me.
Instead of just saying ויאמר יואב לא כי פה אמות Vayomer Yoav
lo ki po amut which is four words, לא כי פה אמות.
Lo ki po amut. It seems like there's a whole conversation. Now
the גמרא's Gemara going to, at least the גמרא's Gemara interpreting it
to mean that there was this whole conversation, a backstory, which is
not in the פסוקים, pesukim, and now we're going to deal with
that whole backstory. אמר ליה זיל
אימא ליה תרתי. Amar leh zil emar leh tarte. So יואב Yoav
said to בניהו, Benayahu, לא תהוי בהאי גברא. Lo tavei behai gavra.
אי קטלת
ליה
קבל לוטיה דלטייה אבוך ואי לא שבקיה דליקום בלוטיה דלטייה אבוך.
I kata'lat leh kabbal lotei delateih abukha,
ve'illelo shavkeh dileikum belotei delatet
abukha. So he says listen, this was back, and this was also
part of the פסוקים pesukim from the last time I did this
דף, daf, that
when
דוד המלך David HaMelekh had found out what had happened, יואב Yoav
had killed אבנר, Avner, he gave him a whole bunch of curses.
And the גמרא's Gemara going to talk about the curses in the,
and we're going to quote those פסוקים. pesukim. So I didn't quote
them now,
didn't do them now, but we're going to go through it. So
he says listen, יואב Yoav got cursed by דוד. David. And now
יואב Yoav is saying,
either let me be with my curses and alive, but don't kill
me and have the curses still in effect. One or the other.
If you kill me, lift the curses, and if you keep the
curses, then you can't kill me. It's not fair to do both.
I mean, because the curses wouldn't just be on him, it was
on him and his family for all generations.
ויאמר לו המלך, Vayomer lo hammelekh, so this is now back to
שלמה, Shlomo, ויאמר לו המלך
עשה כאשר דבר ופגע בו וקברתהו. Vayomer lo hammelekh aseh ka'asher dibber
upaga bo ukvartu. So he says okay, do as he says and
kill him. So do as he says yet again the פשט pshat
was just kill him there as opposed to יואב Yoav said no,
I'm not going to go, you gotta kill me here, right? So
okay, kill him there. So no, do as he says meaning this
whole backstory now about removing these curses, fine. So I accept upon
myself that either the curses stay and he lives or he dies
but no curses. So he's like okay, so I'll accept that. If
I'm going to kill him, that means no curses. So that's what
he means. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב כל קללות שקלל דוד את
יואב נתקיימו בזרעו של דוד. Amar Rav Yehudah Amar Rav kol klalot
shekillal David et Yoav nitkayemu bezaro shel David. So all the curses
that דוד David had cursed יואב Yoav with,
I guess potentially as a result of this, now that these curses
were lifted from יואב, Yoav, now they went back to דוד. David.
So basically it boomerangs.
And the גמרא's Gemara going to talk about that too. האיכא, Ha-ika,
so here were the curses: אל יכרת מבית יואב זב ומצורע ומחזיק
בפלך. Al yakheret mibbeit Yoav zav umetzora umakhazik bapallekh. מחזיק בפלך Makhazik
bapallekh
the way they translate this here
is they need like people who going to be like limping or
lame and they have to use a cane of some sort, support,
מחזיק בפלך. makhazik bapallekh.
ונופל בחרב, Venofel bakherev, you know, dies I mean literally by sword
but it could mean war. By sword, it could mean war. or,
you know, like וחסר לחם. V'chasar Lechem. And the last one is
lacking bread, so you know, so we're going to see. It doesn't
mean that this was for all generations, you know, it doesn't mean
it was all the same person that this happened to. We'll go
through זב ורחבעם. Zav u-Rechav'am. So how do you know that this
happened to one of the... if you... it doesn't have to be
like a child directly of David, but you know, a descendant of
David. זב ורחבעם Zav u-Rechav'am that happened, דכתיב והמלך רחבעם התאמץ לעלות
במרכבה לנוס
ירושלים. Dichtiv v'hamellech Rechav'am hit'ametz la'alot bamerkava lanus Yerushalayim. So the king
Rechav'am, התאמץ, hit'ametz, he made a מאמץ, ma'amatz, he made an effort
to get onto the chariot to run away to Yerushalayim, a מרכבה.
merkava. That's the word we're focusing on, וכתיב וכל המרכב אשר ירכב
עליו הזב
יטמא. U-chtiv v'chol hamerkav asher yirkav alav hazav yitma. So and any
seat, you know, something that's used to support the body's weight that
the זב zav is using, that becomes טמא. tamei. So מרכבה merkava
and מרכב, merkav, so that means of course that Rechav'am was a
זב. zav. מצורע ועוזיהו, Metzora v'Uziyahu, this is... that's sort of reading
into the pasuk, ובמצורע ועוזיהו, U-v'metzora v'Uziyahu, this is explicit. ובחזקתו גבה
לבו עד להשחית וימעל בה' אלוקיו ויבוא אל היכל ה' להקטיר על
מזבח הקטורת. U-v'chez'kato gavah libo ad lehashchit vayimal b'Hashem Elokav vayavo el
heichal Hashem lehaktir al mizbe'ach haktoret.
So the king Uziyahu was actually... he offered the קטורת. ktoret. Now
of course he's not allowed to do that, only the כוהנים kohanim
can do that, right?
That's... so and the pasuk says this, והצרעת זרחה במצחו, V'hatzara'at zarchah
b'mitz'cho,
right away. You know, so he's punished with צרעת. tzara'at. So that's
explicit.
Isn't that a minor offense? Isn't a non-kohen doing the עבודה avodah
a big offense?
Yeah, yeah, I know. I never really quite understood that.
I don't know how to answer that. I have that same problem.
So he got
צרעת. tzara'at. But it could also be that like, you know, in
other words, you know,
what is the punishment, you know, could either be... I think like
the גמרות gemarot talk about like the פרחי כהונה, pirchei kehuna, you
know, or somebody, you know, they get him there or it's like
maybe כרת. karet. But כרת karet is not necessarily... it's not like
God strikes you down right away. So this is like... maybe the
answer would be that this is like, you know, a public sign
of God's displeasure manifesting itself immediately, you know? Like he's not going
to get away with this at all, not even for a moment.
So that could be what it's about. So I mean like, you
know, he still could have gotten punished in some sort of divine
calculation, but this is an immediate punishment right away.
I think in the story he was warned, right, by the... I
can't remember how the rest of the story... but so he got
צרעת. tzara'at. So this is one of
the... so that's one of them, right? So we went through זב
zav and now מצורע. metzora. מחזיק בפלך, Machzik bapelech, so needing support
from,
you
know, from a cane or whatever it was. מי אסא דכתיב ורק
לעת זקנתו חלה את רגליו.
Mi Assa dichtiv v'rak l'et ziknato
chalah et raglav. So when he got old, you know, his legs
were ill, meaning, you know, so he obviously couldn't walk too well.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב שאחזו
פודגרא. V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav she'achazo podagra. So he had
פודגרא, podagra, which here they translate as gout. אמר ליה מר זוטרא
בריה דרב נחמן לרב נחמן, Amar lei Mar Zutra berei d'Rav Nachman
l'Rav Nachman, Mar Zutra the son of Rav Nachman asked his father
Rav Nachman, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What? You know, he didn't know
what gout is. אמר ליה. Amar lei. I mean, and if you
haven't experienced it, you know, it's kind of hard to know what
it really is. So he's like, אמר ליה כמחט בבשר החי. Amar
lei kemachat b'vasar hachai. It's like a needle in... you know, it's
like your flesh is being pierced by a needle. So מנא ידע?
Mina yada? How did he know? איבעית אימא מיחש הוה מחייש ביה,
Iba'it eima michash hava machish bei, he had it. איבעית אימא מרביה
אגמריה, Iba'it eima merabeih agmeireih, he learned it, that's what it... you
know, from his rav in yeshiva. They were discussing gout one day
and, you know, then they were discussing and then he said this
is what it feels like. איבעית אימא סוד ה' ליראיו. Iba'it eima
sod Hashem liyre'av. Sometimes you see that.
ובריתו
להודיעם. U-vrito lehodiam. God's secret to those that fear Him. In other
words, you know, things that, you know, get revealed somehow to those
who are close to God.
And it's sort of like a... sometimes you see this in, you
know, in like yeshiva writings. Like, you know, if you question like
the ruling of a... of you know, someone who you view as
superior to you, but you're questioning it, meaning you don't really agree
with them, you'd be like how do you know this? It must
be סוד ה' ליראיו. sod Hashem liyre'av. You know, he must have
some like secret way of knowing that this is the truth. Anyway,
so ונופל בחרב, V'nofel bacharev, יאשיהו דכתיב ויורו המורים למלך
יאשיהו.
Yoshiyahu dichtiv vayoiru
hamorim lamelech Yoshiyahu. So
he was like, you know, pierced by all these arrows. Yeah, and
then... so again, it doesn't mean sword literally, you know, it means
dying in battle. You know, that's חרב charev is like the catch-all
phrase for that. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב שעשאו כולהו ככברה.
V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav she'asau
kulhu kich'varah. So like, you know, his body's like a sieve, you
know, lots of holes. Like, you know, they... there were 300 arrows
or something like that, right? So he really got pierced by a
lot of arrows. וחסר לחם, V'chasar lechem, so the end of that,
וחסר לחם, v'chasar lechem, lacking bread from יכניה דכתיב ארוחתו ארוחת תמיד
ניתנה לו. Yechonyah dichtiv aruchato aruchat tamid nitna lo. So יכניה... Yechonyah...
Rashi... and there's a mistake in Rashi.
It wasn't... so Nevuchadnezzar captured יכניה Yechonyah and imprisoned him, but then
Nevuchadnezzar's son, I think it was Evil Merodach, right? So freed him
and then provided for him.
So and this sounds like it's a pretty good deal.
Yeah, the captive kings often were treated pretty well.
So... but the reading into this is that... and he and he
had it like לחם lechem the rest of his life, actually. So...
What the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is reading into this is, oh, okay, so Evil-Merodach
gave him food, but when he was with Nevuchadnezzar, he didn't have
any food, so that's חסר לחם *chasar lechem*. So, basically the point
was
that and this is kind of summarizing it. אמר amar, רב היינו
דאמרי אינשי *Amar Rav Haynu d'amre inshi* this fact that all this
happened to דוד David *David*'s progeny is what people say תהא לוטה
ולא תהא לטה *tehey luta v'lo tehey lata*, better to be cursed
than to be the curser. Why? Because you know דוד David, *David*
made יואב Yoav *Yoav* put all these curses, execrations on יואב Yoav.
*Yoav* and what happened, right? They boomeranged onto דוד David *David*. But
then you know, so but that was because of what יואב Yoav
*Yoav* said, you know, you gotta like either keep me with my
curses alive or kill me but the curses. So שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo*
said alright fine, right? This again didn't necessarily mean that you know
all curses have to go back to you but sort of what
goes around comes around, right? So that's now getting back to the
יואב Yoav, *Yoav* story. אתו ליה ליואב דייניה *Atu lei Yoav daynei*.
So again, remember this whole conversation with יואב Yoav *Yoav* and בניהו
Benayahu *Benayahu*, conversation, it seems again according to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
it's a whole conversation but according to the פסוקים pesukim, *Pesukim* it
was very quick. You know בניהו Benayahu *Benayahu* says to יואב Yoav,
*Yoav*, you know, your game's up. יואב Yoav *Yoav* says like I'm
not leaving here. You know he said his four words and then
goes back to the king and you know king sends him and
kills him, right? So but again and it sounds like you know
יואב Yoav, *Yoav* is still you know clinging there, you don't know
how long it took for him to go back to the king
and how long it took the king to send him back but
יואב Yoab *Yoav*, you know the vision you get in your mind
by reading the פסוקים pesukim, *Pesukim* is that יואב Yoab *Yoav* is
still clinging desperately to the corners of the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*, right? But
but you know what did we read recently in the פרשה *parshah*?
לא תקח מעם מזבחי *Lo tikach me'im mizbechi* right?
And then what do we have? שופטים ושוטרים *Shoftim v'shotrim*. So who
is in the general area of the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*, what מסכת *masechet*
are we doing? סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin*, right? So the בתי דין *Batei
Din* are by the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*.
So we're taking it to mean that you know just to ruin
the surprise the next two two words, you know that of course
he didn't kill him in cold blood and have his blood you
know like spill on the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*, rather he brought him to
סנהדרין Sanhedrin. *Sanhedrin* who are by the מזבח *Mizbe'ach* and there's a
whole you know they went through due process. Not like you know
it's not like this is a vigilante killing. The impression you get
clearly is that it's a vigilante killing almost. מדין מלכא *Midin malka*,
you know, but it was extrajudicial, should I say? Not vigilante, extrajudicial.
The king has that right.
So and then that's clearly the impression you know that's what it
sounds like but no here they're saying is that there's this whole
court case, right? So now we're gonna go through it. So אתו
ליה ליואב דייניה *Atu lei Yoav daynei*, the דיינים *dayanim*. So they
they brought him into to be judged and of course bringing him
to be judged is not like in front of the king to
be judged, it's in front of סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* because who and
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* are by the מזבח *Mizbe'ach*.
So אמר ליה amar lei, *Amar lei* or אמרו ליה
*amru lei*, so בניהו Benayahu *Benayahu* I guess he's on the סנהדרין
*Sanhedrin* or just he's you know this discussion is taking place around
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* or the or it should be אמרו ליה *amru lei*
as in the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* the judges said, מאי טעמא קטלתיה לאבנר
*Mai ta'ama katlet l'Avner*? So they're asking יואב Yoab *Yoav* why did
you kill אבנר Avner. *Avner*? אמר ליה amar lei, גואל הדם goel
hadam. הוינא לעשהאל אחי *Amar lei go'el hadam havina l'Asa'el achi*. I
was the גואל הדם Goel HaDam *go'el hadam* of my brother, right?
Remember I said that there were a couple of brothers, יואב Yoab.
*Yoav* was עשהאל Asael, *Asa'el*'s brother and אבנר Avner, *Avner* killed עשהאל
Asahel *Asa'el* who was running after him, that was that whole thing
and that's why דוד David *David* had to make this big protestation
that he had nothing to do with it. So אמר גואל הדם
*amar
go'el
hadam*. So of course I killed him, right? You know the גואל
הדם *go'el hadam* is maybe even מחוייב *mechuyav*, not מחוייב *mechuyav* but
מצווה *mitzvah*, right?
According to some. It was like you know it was a whole
we had three opinions, right? It was מצווה *mitzvah*, אסור *assur* or
you know or מותר *mutar* or so
he אמר
גואל הדם *amar go'el hadam* of עשהאל Asahel *Asa'el*'s death. So then
the answer to this is and this is the whole conversation that
they're having, עשהאל Asahel רודף הוה *Asa'el
rodef
havah*.
So
this is like self this was self defense, right? What do you
mean like you know oh I'm a גואל הדם *go'el hadam* but
like you know עשהאל Asahel *Asa'el* was trying to kill אבנר Avner
*Avner*. So what could אבנר Avner *Avner* have done? You're the גואל
הדם *go'el hadam*. I mean like you know if אבנר Avner *Avner*
had done nothing he would have been killed. So of course this
is a justified you know what is it like justified homicide, right?
So you're not what גואל הדם *go'el hadam*. You know גואל הדם
*go'el hadam* is like you know you kill somebody in cold blood,
right? Or like you know or the ערי מקלט *arei miklat* that
kind of thing, right? But this was like you know you're saving
his own life. So then the answer to that is and then
יואב Yoab *Yoav* now answers to בניהו *Benayahu*, okay fine, והיה לו
להצילו באחד מאיבריו *V'hayu l'atzilo b'achad
me'eivarav*.
Okay, but you know but if the הלכה *halakha* is for that
like you know why do you have to kill him, why couldn't
he just like maim him or something, you know temporarily incapacitate him,
why do you have to kill him? אמר ליה Amar lei, לא
יכל ליה *Amar lei lo yachul lei*. No he couldn't, you know,
like he was running away what else could he have done, like
he didn't he didn't have the opportunity to you know to be
so calculated. אמר ליה Amar lei *Amar lei* of course not. השתא
בדופן חמישית כיון ליה *Hashta b'dofen chamishit kiven lei*. No, he aimed
very precisely. He managed to get him in the fifth rib, דכתיב
De-chtiv, ויכהו אבנר Avner באחרי החנית אל החומש. That’s the פסוק. Pasuk.
So, you know, he managed to, like, take the back end of
his, like, you know, spear or whatever, however you pronounce, whatever-whatever חנית
chanis is. I think it’s a spear. Spear it is. Yeah, so
he got him into the חומש, chomesh, ואמר רבי יוחנן, V’amar Rabi
Yochanan, what does the חומש chomesh mean? דופן חמישית, Dofen chamishis, the
fifth rib, במקום שהמרה והכבד תלויים בו. bimkom shehamara vehakaved teluyim bo.
So, like, you know, like vital organs are there, like the liver.
So he knew what he was doing, you know. He aimed very
precisely. You’re saying he couldn’t, you know, be מציל באחד מאיבריו? matzil
be’achad me’eivarav? דהוה יכול ליה? dehavah yachol lei?
Of course he could. In which case then he, you know, he
could have and he didn’t, which means then he really didn’t need
to kill him and therefore I’m avenging his blood, right? So he’s
saying that he has a justified excuse now for, you know, for
getting him back for that, right?
So basically, so really, like, you know,
he bested him in this טענה, ta’ana, right? So,
okay. So, alright, so בניהו was like, alright, you got me there.
But אמר ליה, ניזיל דאבנר. neizil de’Avner. Alright, fine, let’s let that
one go. But מאי טעמא קטלתיה לעמשא? mai ta’ama kataltei l’Amasa? You
still killed עמשא. Amasa. So אמר
ליה, עמשא מורד במלכות הוה. Amasa mored bemalchus havah.
Amasa was also rebelling against the king, so I had every right
to kill him, I should have killed him. So דכתיב ויאמר המלך
אל עמשא, dechtiv Vayomer hamelech el Amasa, and the funny thing is,
like,
they have this
פסוק pasuk and there’s a much better פסוק pasuk to quote, but
let’s just go with this for the moment. The גמרא, Gemara I
mean, it’s explicitly he’s a מורד במלכות, mored bemalchus, but this is
what they, this is what they go for: הזעק לי את איש
יהודה שלשת
ימים. Hazeik li es ish Yehuda
sheloshes yamim. So he said, the king said, so you got to
get together for me the men of יהודה Yehuda within three days.
So I’m giving you, you know, it takes a while to get
the people together, so I’m giving you three days to do that,
verbalization. וילך עמשא להזעיק את יהודה ויותר.
Vayeilech
Amasa lehazik es Yehuda vayocher.
He did,
but he took a little bit longer, more than those three days.
So, oh, okay, so he took longer than three days, of course
he’s rebelling against the king. So very, very strange. אמר ליה, עמשא
אך ורק
דרש. Amasa ach v’rak darash. He was a justified delay. How so?
אשכחיו דפתחי ביה במסכתא. ashchayu depaschu beih be-masechta.
In other words, what would be, you know, a justified delay? Because
all the people were learning תורה, Torah, so he didn’t want to
interrupt their תורה Torah learning. That’s why it took longer than three
days. So, and he’s going
back: כל איש אשר ימרה את פיך ולא
ישמע את דבריך לכל אשר תצונו יומת.
Kol ish asher yamreh es picha v’lo yishma es devarecha lechol
asher tetzavenu yumas. So anyone, and this is also another interesting thing.
He’s learning this from יהושע. Yehoshua. So would you say יהושע Yehoshua
is like the king, right?
So, in the very beginning when משה Moshe died, this is the
very beginning of יהושע, Yehoshua, you know, there’s this whole back and
forth,
רק חזק ואמץ, rak chazak ve’ematz, and anyone who doesn’t listen to
you, you know, will die. So, you know, basically the nation is
saying we’re backing you
יהושע Yehoshua
fully. So, okay, so anyone who doesn’t listen to you will die.
יכול אפילו לדברי תורה? Yachol afilu le-divrei Torah? But if it involved
דברי תורה, divrei Torah, could you say they have to die? תלמוד
לומר רק חזק ואמץ. Talmud lomar rak chazak ve’ematz. So רק, rak,
I mean, you know, usually a רק rak and an אך ach
is a מיעוט. mi’ut. So what do they learn from that? That
since they were learning תורה, Torah, so עמשא Amasa said, okay, I’m
going to wait a little, let them finish their, you know, their
משמר, mishmar, right? So he waited.
So, you know,
this justifies the refusal of the חרדי Charedi in Israel to serve
in the army, apparently.
We’re still trying to prove that he was
מורד במלכות.
mored bemalchus. Yeah, so he, so another, so remember, like, you know,
so יואב Yoab is trying to kill, בניהו is trying to kill
off יואב. Yoab יואב Yoab killed off two guys. One was יואב,
Yoab one was אבנר. Avner He’s like, okay, yeah, that was justified.
But then אבנר, Avner you know, through this back and forth, said,
no, it was very
justified. יואב Yoab said it was very justified. Okay, he’s like, alright,
but you killed somebody else, עמשא. Amasa. He’s like, what do you
mean? Amasa, I had every right to kill עמשא. Amasa. Amasa was
a מורד במלכות. mored bemalchus. He didn’t get the guys in three
days. Now you are saying no, it wasn’t מורד במלכות. mored bemalchus.
He was justified in waiting to take longer than three days because
they were learning תורה, Torah, they didn’t want to interrupt them.
So סנהדרין says יואב, Yoav no, you’re the מורד במלכות. mored bemalchus.
ואיהו גופיה מורד במלכות הוה דכתיב והשמועה באה עד יואב כי יואב
נטה אחרי אדוניה ואחרי אבשלום לא נטה, V’ihu gufei mored bemalchus havah
dechtiv vehashmuah ba’ah ad Yoav ki Yoav natah acharei Adoniyah v’acharei Avshalom
lo natah, which is what I started with, right? That יואב Yoav
was
backing one of the other people for king. Remember שלמה Shlomo was
king at this time, and if he’s backing one of the other
brothers, that’s מורד במלכות. mored bemalchus.
So
you
are the מורד במלכות mored bemalchus and you need to be killed.
So basically the idea is, I mean, you know, it doesn’t say
whether they bought this argument or not, but that, you know, of
him being justified
or not for killing the second guy,
עמשא. Amasa. But anyway, no matter what, he was a מורד במלכות,
mored bemalchus, יואב, Yoav so he deserves to die. of that. And
then they said like, oh that you know so the גמרא Gemara
is going to be דרשן darshen this פסוק pasuk that he turned
after אדוניה Adoniyah but not after אבשלום. Avshalom. מאי לא נטה? Mai
lo natah? Why do you have to say that, you know, if
he's backing one and he's not backing the other, right? You could
have just said that he backed that he backed אדוניה. Adoniyah. So
what's with that?
That so he says מאי לא נטה? Mai lo natah? אמר רבי
יהושע בן קרחה, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua bin Korcha, שביקש לנטות ולא נטה.
shebikesh lintot velo natah. He wanted to, but he didn't. מאי טעמא
לא נטה? Mai ta'ama lo natah? אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar,
עדיין לכלוכית של דוד קיימת, adayin lichluchit shel David kayyamet, which is
interesting. Like the moisture of דוד David was around, meaning like the
vestiges of דוד'ס David's power were still around and he felt scared
backing backing,
you know, at that point. רבי יוסי... Rabbi Yosi...
anyone else? רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yosi be-Rabbi Chanina אמר, what
does that mean? עדיין אצטגניני של דוד קיימת, adayin istagnine shel David
kayyamet, which is a very interesting word. You know, usually when you
think of אצטגנינים, istagninim, you think of like the, you know, the
sorcerers of like פרעה, Paroh, פרעה'ס Paroh's court, like, you know. So
what what the גמרא Gemara here takes it to mean is, אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, ארבע מאות ילדים
היו לו לדוד, arba me'ot yeladim hayu lo le-David, and remember I
said like, you know, that I that this is like in some
ways a continuation of that דף daf I taught and we this
was from that דף. daf. That there were 400, he had 400
children, כולם בני יפת תואר היו, kulam benei yefat to'ar hayu, remember
that? That they all had they were all like, you know, children
of from war, from the captives. So they're all 400, ומגדלי בלוריות
היו, u-megadlei beloryot hayu, מהלכים בראשי גייסות היו, mehalchim be-rashei gaysot hayu,
והם היו בעלי אגרופין של דוד. ve-hem hayu ba'alei egrofin shel David.
So, you know, and they were like these big, strong, you know,
burly guys and they all they had like this בלורית belorit which
was like that braid which is a thing of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah and over there we dealt with like מנהגי הגויים, minhagei hagoyim,
how were they able to do that? And you know, and I
think what we said over there was, you know, if you're potentially
כובש המלכות, kovesh hamalchut, there's dispensations for war, you know, things like
that. But not, you know, so they were the head of they
were at the head of the armies and you know they
they instilled fear.
His strongmen. His what?
His janissaries?
Yes.
So non-Jewish women who he had the children with produced these great
women.
Yeah, so like you know so he you
know so that's so that's who they were.
Him having wives and ten concubines the...
yeah but right but again these were בני יפת תואר. benei yefat
to'ar. But you know that was the question also, are you allowed
to you know be with this יפת תואר?
yefat to'ar? I'm sorry? Not all of the...
right, so meaning like if you right so meaning יפת תואר yefat
to'ar counts as a you know, it could be and that's a
מחלוקת, machloket, are you allowed to be with this יפת תואר yefat
to'ar once and then go through a whole ritual? We just read
this in כי תצא, Ki Tetze, right? You know, is are you
allowed to be with her once and then you go through a
whole ritual to continue, or you're are you not even allowed to
be with her at all, have sex with her until you go
through the whole ritual? So that was a question. So you know,
anyway, it is a little bit difficult to reconcile all this. But
so that's so one say לכלוכית של דוד lichluchit shel David was
that this, that these were these אצטגנינים, istagninim, meaning
the, you know, again, strange word, but like these people. That that's
the לכלוכית של דוד, lichluchit shel David, like he still had these
400, you know, strong guys and he didn't want to יואב Yoav
didn't want to rumble with them. So
that was what they mean by לכלוכית. lichluchit. Meaning like לא כהתה
עינו ולא נס לחה, lo kahatah eino velo nas lechah, they said
about משה, Moshe, you know, his throat never got dry. So it
basically means that he's still like, you know, has a certain sense
of vitality. So that's what it means. דוד'ס David's vitality or vigor,
you know, was was still around and
he didn't want to contend with that. So פליגי בה רבי אבא
בר כהנא, Pligi bah Rabbi Abba bar Kahana, דאמר רבי אבא בר
כהנא, de-amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana, אלמלא דוד לא עשה יואב מלחמה,
ilmalei David lo asah Yoab milchamah, ואלמלא יואב לא עסק דוד בתורה.
ve-ilmalei Yoab lo asak David ba-Torah. So this is different. You know,
by saying that he always had wanted to rebel, because they weren't
at the same time, אדוניה Adoniyah and אבשלום Avshalom necessarily. So
so here this is saying that you know יואב Yoav had always
wanted to go away from דוד, David he just couldn't because he
was too scared. So this is this is not going according to
that opinion that says that דוד David and יואב Yoav had a
really good partnership and you know they really helped each other out.
That one helped you know that one helped the other learn תורה,
Torah, that דוד David would be able to learn תורה Torah because
he had such a capable general in יואב. Yoav And the other
way around too, that and דוד'ס David's תורה זכות Torah zechut helped
יואב Yoav in in all the wars. דכתיב, ויהי דוד עשה משפט
וצדקה לכל עמו ויואב בן צרויה על הצבא. Vayehi David oseh mishpat
u-tzedakah le-chol ammo ve-Yoab ben Tzeruyah al ha-tzava. That דוד David would
be doing משפט mishpat and צדקה tzedakah and יואב Yoav is on
על הצבא. al ha-tzava. Of course, how do you do משפט mishpat
and צדקה? tzedakah? By learning תורה, Torah, right? So מה טעם דוד
עשה משפט וצדקה לכל עמו? mah ta'am David asah mishpat u-tzedakah le-chol
ammo? משום דויואב על הצבא. mishum de-ve-Yoab al ha-tzava. ומה טעם יואב
על הצבא? ve-mah ta'am Yoab al ha-tzava? Why was he so successful
in his military endeavors? משום דדוד עושה משפט וצדקה לכל עמו. mishum
de-David oseh mishpat u-tzedakah le-chol ammo.
Okay. So which means that they, you know, they had a nice
partnership and liked it. So יואב Yoav, was not according to this
opinion
always trying to break away from it. ויצא יואב, Vayetzei Yoab, going
back to this, ויצא יואב מעם דוד וישלח מלאכים אחרי אבנר וישיבו
אתו מבור הסירה. vayetzei Yoab me-im David vayishlach malachim acharei Avner vayashivu
oto mi-bor ha-Sirah. This is this getting back to how you know
what יואב Yoav did.
Remember, so according to the פסוקים, pesukim יואב Yoav
draws
אבנר aside and you know and in there it says דוד didn't
know. וישב אבנר, Vayashav Avner, this is not in there, וישב אבנר
חברון ויטהו יואב אל תוך השער לדבר אתו בשלי. Vayashav Avner Chevron
vayattehu Yoab el toch ha-sha'ar ledabber itto bashali. And the גמרא'ס Gemara's
going to talk about that. So, you know, בשלי bashali means like,
you know, secret matters or state matters to tell you. יואב draws
him
aside and Right, so then Joab gets him in the fifth rib
like we were explaining and kills him to avenge his his brother
עשהאל, Asahel right? And that's what that whole conversation we were just
backfilling, you know? He killed my brother and now I'm גואל הדם.
Anyway, getting back to that,
מאי בור וסירה, Mai Bor veSira, what's this בור וסירה? bor vesira?
אמר רבי אבא בר כהנא בור וסירה גרמו לאבנר שיהרג. Amar Rabbi
Abba bar Kahana bor vesira garmu leAvner sheyehareg. So the בור bor
and the סירה, sira, these these two things were Abner's downfall. בור
וסירה, Bor veSira, what is that?
רש״י Rashi explains, let's just read רש״י. Rashi. בור צפחת המים שלקח
דוד מחניתותיו של שאול כשהיה ישן במעגל. Bor tzapachat hamayim shelakach David
machanitotav shel Shaul kshehayah yashen bamaagal.
So there were a couple of times, you know, Shaul had it
in for David and always wanted to kill him. And so David
was always trying to show him how faithful he was and that
he's not trying to rebel against him. So the רש״י Rashi is
going through two times in נביא Navi that David proved that like
I could have gotten you and I didn't. One was when, you
know, God had made everyone sleep, you know, and there was like
this like bowl of water, right? So you know, which was right
by שאול׳ס, Shaul's, you know, body, his head.
And showed that he could have.
Yeah, and he took the bowl of water, you know,
and he's like, oh, you know,
guess what? And then and and every time Abner was telling him
every time that, you know, maybe like whatever, David didn't have this
real chance, you know, maybe someone gave it to him, maybe this,
maybe that. So we're going through that now in the רש״י. Rashi.
שאמר להם דוד בני מות אתם שלא שמרתם את אדוניכם. She'amar lahem
David benei mavet atem shelo shamartem et adoneichem. And David is saying,
listen you guys, you soldiers, you bodyguards of Shaul, you guys are
derelict in your duties, you deserve to be death put to death
because you didn't watch Shaul well enough, שכבר הייתי יכול להרגו, shekevar
hayiti yachol lehargo, I could have
I could have killed him. והנה איפה חניתך וצפחת המים, Vehineh eifoh
chanitcha vetzapachat hamayim,
I have your spear and you know this water bowl. So אבנר
should have said, היה לו לאבנר לומר לשאול ראה כמה צדיק הוא
זה שלא הרגך. hayah lo leAvner lomar leShaul re'eh kamah tzaddik hu
zeh shelo hargacha. He should have said, yeah, you know, David is
a good guy, he really could have. Instead, what did he say?
לא מיכלא אמר שמא אחד
מבני הצבא נתנם לו. Lo michla amar shema echad mibnei hatzava netanam
lo. Maybe one of the you got it somehow, you bribed somebody.
That was the בור. bor. וסירה, veSira, and וסירה veSira is a
thorn. So it's like a קוץ. kotz. And now the רש״י Rashi
explains, next רש״י, Rashi, שכרת דוד את כנף מעילו של שאול במערה
עשאהו דטיפתים. shekarat David et knaf meilo shel Shaul bamearah asahu dtei
patim. He, you know, cut off a corner of שאול׳ס Shaul's cloak
with his sword. So היה לו לאבנר לומר לשאול כנ״ל ראה כמה
חסתי עליך ולא הרגתיך בהיותך יחד עמי במערה. hayah lo leAvner lomar
leShaul kanal re'eh kamah chasti alecha velo hargaticha biheyotcha yachad imi bamearah.
He should have said, you're right, you know, David is a good
guy, he could have killed you, look how much he loves you,
stop this, you know, running after David to kill him. But he
didn't. ולא אמר לו כן אלא אמר שמא כשעברת אצל קוצים והסירים
והסתבכת מן הקוצים בכנף מעילך והיה טמון שם וחתכה. velo amar lo
ken ela amar shema kshe'avarta eitzel kotzim vehasirim vehistabachta min hakotzim bichnaf
meilecha vehayah tamun sham vechatachah. So David was hiding amongst the thorn
bushes, you know, you were walking by, a thorn, you know, snagged
your
garment, a part of it got over there, David took it. It's
not like he came to you and could have killed you while
you were asleep and didn't, right? So anyway, so these two things
were Abner's downfall. Now remember, you know, again, this is getting back
to like גמרא Gemara gave it at the time, what did we
say what did we say at the time there? You know, we
went through this whole thing about
about about, you know, what was what was his downfall and we
said, you know, מיכלא ולא מיכלא, Michla velo michla, right? Could he
have, you know, like he said, oh, you know, was David was
David like giving a was David bemoaning the fact or was he
or was he, you know, saying no, you know, was the subject
with נוב? Nov? Remember that? You know, נוב עיר הכהנים, Nov ir
hakohanim, right? That, according to the גמרא Gemara. there, that potentially could
have been his downfall. Like, you know, that he didn't protest against
the killing of נוב עיר הכהנים. Nov ir hakohanim. Was he saying
to like, you know,
that was your downfall, you should have protested and you didn't, right?
And that's why your or was it like when he was saying,
oh, you did protest and even then look what happened here. That
was a debate in the גמרא Gemara we had earlier in סנהדרין.
But they're not bringing that in here now. They're saying about the
these two things caused causes his downfall. Interesting, you know? So different
גמרות Gemaros say different things.
You know, there's a phrase, I don't know if you remember, when
they're talking about the destruction of the of the of the temple,
right? It says because of a of a I can't remember, a
wheel and a you know this whole you know what I'm saying?
It's a similar kind of phraseology here they talk they speak of
two things that caused the destruction and here they're talking about the
pit and the thorn. Do you remember what I'm talking about?
Not a hundred percent, but maybe if you showed it to me
I might have to find it.
Okay, so anyway, so that's what they're saying these two things are,
those two words. I'll go back to the גמרא. Gemara אמר רבי
אבא בר כהנא בור וסירה גרמו לאבנר שיהרג ויטהו יואב אל תוך
השער לדבר אתו בשלי. Amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana bor vesira garmu
leAvner sheyehareg vayatehu Yoav el toch hashaar ledaber ito bashali. So he,
you know, he brings him aside to talk to him
בשלי. bashali. What is that? You know, again, it means שלי, shali,
like, you know, these he whispered to him, like, you know, these
state secrets or whatever it is. That's what's really פשט. pshat. אמר
רבי יוחנן שדנו כדין סנהדרי. Amar Rabbi Yochanan shedano kedin Sanhedri. So
again, I mean, of course everything is not being done
extrajudicially. They brought him as
a he well here so not that he actually brought him to
the סנהדרין because you know that that we can't say because you
all just killed him you know and this wasn't in the סנהדרין
but he you know he went through some sort of like due
process so he says אמר ליה of course there's a whole conversation
אמר ליה מאי טעמא קטלתיה
לעשהאל Amar lei mai ta'ama
kataltiya l'Asahel so why'd you kill עשהאל Asahel so the answer is
sort of what we had before right this is now this is
יואב and אבנר before it's בניהו and יואב right so this is
you know take you know this is going back to the past
a little מאי טעמא קטלתיה לעשהאל Mai ta'ama kataltiya l'Asahel why'd you
kill עשהאל
עשהאל רודף היה Asahel rodeph hayah so עשהאל was you know עשהאל
was running after me so he said היה לך להצילו באחד מאיבריו
Hayah lecha l'hatzilo b'echad me'eivarav you should've killed him off you know
you should've just you know somehow disabled him so לא יכלתי Lo
yacholti I couldn't השתא בדוקא בחומש כיוונת ליה ובאחד מאיבריו לא יכלת
ליה Hashtah b'davka b'chomesh kivanta lei u'b'echad me'eivarav lo yachalta lei
so what do you mean you you get him you got him
precisely in the fifth rib too right
and here the theme is what goes around comes around right because
יואב killed אבנר in the fifth rib just like אבנר killed עשהאל
in the fifth rib and then you know and then and דוד
cursed יואב and then what happened it ended up back boomeranging and
getting you know and happening according to the גמרא Gemara to the
children of דוד so it was this whole like cycle over
here so anyway so therefore he killed him so he's like you
know that's not true you didn't you know you you know you
could've disabled him and you chose not to so you killed him
in the fifth rib therefore I'm killing you right and but according
you know but again according to the גמרא Gemara though like that
you know that was true so now יואב is now גואל הדם
right of עשהאל you know that so now couldn't get get יואב
on that count that's why he had to get him on another
count either the you know either the either because עמשא Amasa or
מורד במלכות Mored B'Malchut anyway you know one or the other okay
getting back to that ויבאהו אותו בשלי Vayavi'u oto bashali what was
that about אמר רב יהודה אמר רב על עסקי נשלי Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav al iskei nashli extend the yud as a vav
and not שלי sheli על עסקי שללו al iskei shallo and what
do you see from שללו shallo של נעליך מעל רגליך Shal ne'alecha
me'al raglecha right God says to משה Moshe take away your remove
your feet so now what is that
about so look at look at רש"י Rashi לשון של נעליך שאלו
באלמנה יבמה גידמת איך חולצת Lashon shal ne'alecha she'alo b'almanah yevamah gidemet
eich choletzet so let's say you know what you're supposed to do
is the יבמה yevamah let's say there's a חליצה chalitzah right so
you know you're supposed to remove the shoe right but let's say
she has no arms how are you supposed to remove the shoe
so so he's like okay התחיל שוחה לפניה ומראה לה כך היא
חולצת בשיניה Hitchil shocheh lefaneha u'mareh lah kach hi choletzet b'shineha so
he's like you know contorting himself this is how you do it
you know you take your teeth she takes her teeth and she
like does it this way so while he was of course doing
the halachic thing because you know of course everyone's always everyone's a
big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham in these things and of course they're
learning תורה Torah so he was busy you know thinking about how
to show him then he kills him that's how he managed to
get him I mean you know the basic idea also is like
look this guy is you know is a pretty competent military man
how'd he manage to get him so off
guard so so he distracted him
basically with תורה Torah so anyway but like the whole you know
but he's saying but you know but we're trying to say is
that this you know but he but there was a whole according
to the גמרא Gemara there's a whole conversation now he's like oh
you should this that the other you you know you're I'm justified
killing you so and it wasn't like vigilantism 100% even though really
somewhat was so okay והכיתו אל החומש V'hikitu el hachomesh אמר רבי
יוחנן דחבקו בחמישית ובמקום שמהרבא כבד וטחול תלויין
בו
Amar Rabi Yochanan
d'chabko b'chamishit u'b'makom she'marah kaved v'tichol tluyim
bo
like we said before he got him on the fifth rib which
is very fatal והשיב השם את דמו על ראשו אשר פגע בשני
אנשים צדיקים וטובים ממנו V'heshiv Hashem et damo al rosho asher paga
b'shnei anashim tzadikim v'tovim mimenu like we said that שלמה was saying
that this יואב has to be killed because he killed two people
better than him we read that in the in the in the
beginning so how what in what way were they better שהיו דורשים
אכין ורקין והוא לא דרש She'hayu dorshin achin v'rakin v'hu lo darash
so they were דורשין dorshin all these אכין ורקין achin v'rakin in
the in the תורה Torah and he didn't what do we mean
by that so again רש"י Rashi לשון שמה שלא קיים מצות המלך
לבוא על דברי תורה lashon shama shelo kiyam mitzvat hamalech lavo al
divrei torah אמר זכור תזכרנה אבנר כשהיה עם שאול ועבדיו סבו בבית
כנסת של קונה השם וגומר וכתיב לא אבו עבדי שאול לשלוח ידם
בכהני
ה' Amar zachor tizkarena Avner kesheh hayah im Shaul v'avadav sabu b'veit
knesset shel koneh Hashem v'gomer u'chtiv lo avu avdei Shaul lishloach yadam
b'kohanei Hashem so עמשא Amasa what is it עמשא Amasa is like
he was דורש daresh this אך ach and רק rak meaning not
to get the people within the three days as they're too busy
learning תורה Torah right so these guys they were דורש daresh the
אך ach and the רק rak and what was יואב I mean
אבנר was what so this is that whole question we had before
about נוב Nov did he protest against נוב Nov or not right
so the גמרא wasn't so sure you know whether he protested according
to this opinion he did so so you know look they knew
how to stand up right if the king had an unjustified command
so you should've stood up you should've you
should've also just following orders right that's not that's not a good
argument right so that's what he's saying והוא לא דרש V'hu lo
darash and he didn't דורש daresh what did he not דורש daresh
the famous story of ההוא דהרג אוריה במצותו של דוד Hahu d'harag
Uriyah b'mitzvato shel David right אוריה
החתי Uriyah HaChiti was killed you know by the king's command and
here. יואב was instrumental in that.
And the גמרא's going to continue with that. So they're דרשן darshan
ארקו נערקו לדרשא דכיון דבפירוש לא כתיבו בהו באיגרתא עשא. arku ne'arku
l'drasha d'keivan d'beferush lo ktivu behu b'igarta asa.
So they were told explicitly by the king to carry out his
commands and they didn't.
And but יואב, you know, he was sent a letter by the
king. דוד didn't actually command it
explicitly to his mouth, he sent a letter doing it and he
could have, it's much easier to obey a letter than his command
from the king, so he should have disobeyed it and especially if
it was done by a letter, but he didn't.
So they're better than you.
עמשא Amasa did not, you know, watch
out to protect himself against
his military accoutrements that יואב had. אמר רב שלא חשדו. Amar Rav
shelo chashado. He didn't even suspect anything. וקבורה טוב במדבר. v'kevura tov
b'midbar. So that was the end of that, he was buried in
his house in the desert. על ביתו
במדבר. al beito b'midbar. Who has a house in the desert? Right?
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב כמדבר, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav k'midbar,
not that his house was in the desert but his house was
like a desert. מה מדבר
מופקר לכל, mah midbar mufkar lakol, just like a מדבר's midbar free
and open to anybody,
אף ביתו של יואב מופקר לכל. af beito shel Yoav mufkar lakol.
Like anyone could come in and he was basically very generous with
his money, he supported the poor. דבר אחר כמדבר, davar acher k'midbar,
מה מדבר נקי מגזל ועריות, mah midbar naki migezel v'arayot, you know,
no sin is in the מדבר, midbar, there's no stealing, there's no
licentiousness, אף ביתו של יואב נקי מגזל ועריות. af beito shel Yoav
naki migezel v'arayot.
So despite the fact, you know, we're saying how bad he was,
but he was also pretty good. ויואב יחיה את שאר העיר. v'Yoav
yichaye et shear ha'ir. So
יואב brought יחיה, yichaye, sorry, he brought life to the city. אמר
יהודה אפילו מוניני ותחננא טעים. Amar Yehuda afilu monini v'tachanana ta'im.
So, you know, הריס להו. haris lahu. So all the delicacies that
he had, he used to give out. Alright, let's turn the דף.
daf.
And that's specifically referring to ירושלים, Jerusalem, that's what we're talking about.
So we have a few minutes, this'll go quickly.
The עמוד ב'. amud bet. We'll do what we can. So remember
we talked before about סקילה. sekila. So ארבע מיתות בית דין, arba
mitot bet din, סקילה שריפה הרג וחנק, sekila serefa hereg v'chenek, four
מיתות. mitot. So someone should have said this earlier. Yes,
four, stoning, burning, again we're not going to talk about them all
now but this is a catch-all introduction. הרג hereg is beheading, חנק
chenek is strangulation. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, so he switches
it a little bit, שריפה סקילה חנק והרג. serefa sekila chenek v'hereg.
Right, he switches the order. זו מיתה הנסקלת. zo mita haniskala. What
we talked about
before was the stoning thing. You know, we said that before, you
take him up שתי קומות, shtei komot, you push him off, that
whole thing. Okay. אמר הונא אמר רב אשכורא אמר רב הונא, Amar
Huna Amar Rav Askorei Amar Rav Huna, כל מקום ששנו חכמים דרך
מניין, kol makom sheshanu chakhamim derekh minyan, אין מוקדם ומאוחר, ein mukdam
u'me'uchar,
חוץ משבעה סממנים. chutz mi'shiva samamin. So here we had a list,
these four. So oftentimes when we have a list it's not in
any particular order, sometimes they are. One of them is this case.
תנן שבעה סממנים מעבירין על הכתם tnan shiva samamin ma'avirin al haketem
to see if something is actually דם נידה, dam nida, you put
in, you rub it with these like seven cleaning agents and if
it stays or doesn't turn a certain color or whatever, then you
know it's דם נידה. dam nida. And these are those. We're not
going to get into them specifically. רוק תפל, rok tafel, saliva, מגסין,
magisin, chewed beans, מי רגליים mei raglayim is urine, נתר neter and
בורית, borit, קמוניא, kimonia, אשלג. ashlag.
All these things, not important right now what they are. וקתני סיפא,
v'katani seifa, העבירן שלא כסדרן או שהעבירן שבען כאחד לא עשה ולא
כלום. he'eviran shelo k'sidran o she'he'eviran shivan k'echad lo asa velo klum.
So again, we said most of the time the list is in
no particular order, but in this case it is. If you went
out of
order, then no good. So that list is very specific. רב פפא
סבא משמיה דרבא אמר, Rav Papa saba mishmei d'Rava amar, אף ארבע
מיתות. af arba mitot. This is another case, our משנה. mishna. These
four are in a specific order. How do we know? מדקמיפלג רבי
שמעון, mi'dkamiflig Rabbi Shimon,
שמע מינה דדווקא תנא. shem mina d'davka tana. Because רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says no, it's a
different order, so
obviously the
תנא קמא tana kama who had it in his order was very
specific, it needs to be this order.
ואידך. v'idakh. Okay, so remember אשכורא Askorei said he only listed the
seven things for the דם נידה. dam nida. Why didn't he list
our משנה? mishna? בלבדי לא קאמיירי bilvudei lo kama'irei because there's a
מחלוקת. machloket. Obviously, it goes without saying he's talking about something where
there's just a list and no one's disagreeing. So רב פפא
אמר, Rav Papa amar, another although we said these are the exceptions,
there's more. סדר יומא. seder yoma. דתנן ditnan כל מעשה יום הכיפורים
אמורין על
הסדר,
kol ma'aseh yom
hakippurim amurin al haseder, everything regarding יום כיפור Yom Kippur has to
be in that order. אם הקדים מעשה לחבירו לא עשה ולא כלום,
im hikdim ma'aseh lachavero lo asa velo klum, it has to be
in that order.
So he adds the יום כיפור Yom Kippur סדר. seder. So why
didn't אשכורא Askorei add that? רב אידך Rav Idakh ההוא חומרא דיומא.
hahu chumra d'yoma. So meaning yes, it's not because of the סדר,
seder, it's not so much in the סדר seder but it's because
of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So it's a slight distinction. It's not the
סדר seder that's important but it's the עיצומו של יום itzumo shel
yom that's important which demands the
סדר. seder. So take it or leave it. Another addition: רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע אמר Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua amar אף סדר
תמיד af seder tamid דקתני עלה d'katani aleha זהו סדר התמיד. zehu
seder hatamid. Talking about the קרבן תמיד Korban Tamid that’s done a
certain
way and it mentions that, that’s a סדר תמיד. Seder Tamid. ואידך?
V’idach? So why was this not on the list? הוא מצוה בעלמא.
Hu mitzvah b’alma. That’s actually what he’s saying is as a matter
of fact, obviously you have to שחט shacht it before putting the
limbs on the altar, but other than that,
this limb or that limb first on the altar, that makes no
difference. So actually he would disagree and says that the סדר תמיד
Seder Tamid is not so precise.
It’s the preference but it’s not
מעכב. me’akev. ולאפוקי מצות חליצה. U’l’appukei mitzvat chalitzah. And so again some
of these other lists are taking out, it’s not including
מצות חליצה. mitzvat chalitzah. דתנן מצות חליצה בהוא והיא ובבית דין. Detnan
mitzvat chalitzah b’hu v’hi u’v’beit din. So the two people involved in
this, the person who’s supposed to get יבום yibbum and the
יבם, yavam, the guy who’s supposed to be doing it, if they
don’t want to do it, they both go to the בית דין.
beit din. ונותנים לו עצה הוגנת לו. Ve’notnim lo eitzah hogenet lo.
So the court gives him advice appropriate to him which basically means
to a point of say she’s too not fit for
him, let’s say he’s old, she’s young, it’s not fair, you shouldn’t
do יבום. yibbum. So those kind of things. Or the other way
around where he’s too old for the other. Anyway, stuff like that.
Okay, so then they assess the situation, give the appropriate advice, שנאמר
וקראו לו זקני עירו ודברו אליו. shene’emar v’karu lo ziknei iro v’dibru
eilav. They’re going to talk to him. So what do they talk
to him about? That. והיא אומרת. V’hi omeret. And then she says,
אין מאן יבמי להקים לאחיו שם בישראל לא אבה יבמי. ein m’ein
yevami l’hakim l’achiv shem b’Yisrael lo avah yabmi. So he doesn’t want
to do it then. And then לא אבה יבמי, lo avah yabmi,
my יבם yavam refuses to do this. והוא אומר לא חפצתי לקחתה.
V’hu omer lo chafatzti l’kachatah. And he says no I don’t want
to marry her. ושנו בלשון הקדש היו אומרים. Oshnu b’lashon ha’kodesh hayu
omrim. And they have to say this all in Hebrew. ונגשה יבמתו
לעיני הזקנים וחלצה נעלו מעל רגלו וירקה בפניו. V’nigshah yevamto l’einai hazekeinim
v’chaltzah na’alo me’al raglo v’yarkah b’fanav.
So she has to then take the shoe off and she has
to spit in front of him. וענתה ואמרה ככה יעשה לאיש אשר
לא יבנה את בית אחיו. Ve’anata v’amrah kachah ye’aseh la’ish asher lo
yivneh et beit achiv.
This is what will be done, she says this, meaning this whole
process. ונקרא שמו בישראל בית חלוץ הנעל. V’nikra shemo b’Yisrael beit chalutz
ha’na’al. And then his name will be known in Israel as the
house of the removed shoe. So okay, so there’s a whole order
here. ואמר רב יהודה מצות חליצה קורא וקורא
וחולצת ורוקקת וקורא. V’amar Rav Yehuda mitzvat chalitzah korah v’kora v’choletzet v’roreket
v’kora. So all these פסוקים, pesukim she reads, he reads, she does
the חליצה, chalitzah, the spitting and then she says this פסוק. pasuk.
סברנא בהא כמה דלמדינן היא. Savirna b’hai kama d’lamdinan hi. We know
that. What do you need to tell us that’s the order? The
פסוקים go through it, the משנה Mishna goes through it. הא קא
משמע לן מצוה הכי דאי אפיק לית לן
בה.
Ha kamashma lan mitzvah hachi
di’afik leit lan bah. Meaning this is why it’s not on the
list. Yes, the פסוקים say it, the משנה Mishna says it, but
it wasn’t on the list of things that have to be in
a particular order because if you change the order, no biggie, no
problem. I mean the מצוה mitzvah is to do it that way
but you can change the order. That’s why it didn’t make the
list of things that have to be דוקא davka in that order.
תניא הכי בין שקדם חליצה לרקיקה או רקיקה לחליצה מה שעשה עשוי.
Tanya hachi bein she’kidem chalitzah l’rekikah o rekikah l’chalitzah mah she’asah asui.
If you do one the רקיקה rekikah or the חליצה chalitzah one
before the other, what you’ve done is done, you’re good. So it
doesn’t have to be לעיכובא, l’ikuva, it’s not לעיכובא. l’ikuva. Just a
few more lines and then we’re done. ולאפוקי מהא, U’l’appukei me’ha, and
this would exclude דתנן
כל המשמש בשמונה כלים.
detnan kol hameshammesh
b’shmonah
keilim. A כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has eight garments. והדיוט בארבעה. V’hedyot
b’arba’ah. And a כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot has four. What are they?
כתונת ומכנסיים מצנפת ואבנט. Ketonet u’michnasayim mitznefet v’avneit. That’s what the תורה
Torah says actually in that order. Yeah, the כתונת, ketonet, the long
robe, מכנסיים michnasayim are like the shorts, מצנפת mitznefet is that hat,
אבנט avneit is the belt. מוסיף עליהם כהן גדול חושן אפוד מעיל
וציץ. Mosif aleihem Kohen Gadol choshen ephod me’il v’tzitz. The כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol had those other things. דתניא מנין שיהא דבר קודם למכנסיים
שנאמר ומכנסי בד יהיו על בשרו. Detanya minayin she’yei davar kodem l’michnasayim
shene’emar u’michnesei bad yihyu al besaro. So basically it doesn’t make so
much of a difference of what order you put them on. Obviously
you have to put the מכנסיים michnasayim first. I mean in some
ways it does. I mean you can’t put the outer garments on
before the other ones. But you can put like let’s say the
אפוד ephod before the ציץ tzitz or whatever it is, or the
ציץ tzitz before the אפוד, ephod, that kind of stuff. ואמרי בה
תניא מאי טעמא אקדמי לכתונת? Ve’amri bah tanya mai ta’ama akdimi l’ketonet?
So if it doesn’t make a difference,
or rather why did the תנא Tanna say כתונת ketonet before מכנסיים?
michnasayim? Obviously you have to put on the underwear before the thing
over it. משום דאקדמיה קרא. Mishum d’akdemia kra.
Because the תורה Torah mentions it first. וקרא מאי טעמא אקדמיה? V’krah
mai ta’ama akdemia? So if really you have to put on the
מכנסיים michnasayim before the כתונת, ketonet, why did the תורה Torah mention
it first. משום דמכסה כולי גופא עדיפא ליה. Mishum d’michaseh kulei gufa
adifah leh.
Because the כתונת ketonet covers the whole body so they wanted to
mention
that as opposed to מכנסיים, michnasayim, but as between those two which
have to be in a specific order, the rest of the stuff
doesn’t have to be in a particular order according to that תנא
Tanna that didn’t include it on that list. And we’re done for
today. יישר
כח.
Yashar
koach.
These halakhic fast sections are much easier.
Yes. Or also because I try to be...